<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-16T09:27:28+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">N. Rajewsky Lab | Max Delbrück Center</title><subtitle>Systems Biology of Gene Regulatory Elements</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Publication alert: our current thoughts on spatial transcriptomics</title><link href="/blog/pathology-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Publication alert: our current thoughts on spatial transcriptomics" /><published>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/pathology-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/pathology-review"><![CDATA[<h2 id="challenges--opportunities-in-clinical-translation-of-high-resolution-spatial-transcriptomics-st">Challenges &amp; Opportunities in Clinical Translation of High-Resolution Spatial Transcriptomics (ST)</h2>

<p>🧬  Spatial transcriptomics technologies revolutionized our ability to profile gene expression in intact tissue sections at subcellular resolution!</p>

<p>🔬  Since Virchow, pathology has always been fueled by technological advances and these ‘molecular microscopes’ hold great potential to identify disease mechanisms and guide therapuetic choices.</p>

<p>🏥  Curious to know how they work and how they can be translated into the clinic?
Our thoughts are now out on <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/content/journals/10.1146/annurev-pathmechdis-111523-023417">Annual Reviews of Pathology</a>.</p>

<p>🚀  Digitalizing gene expression &amp; tissue morphology is already generating the training data for the next generation large-scale models, bridging histology and molecular biology for pathology 2.0. We are excited to see what the future holds!</p>

<p>High-resolution ST technologies work as molecular microscopes, digitalizing gene expression and tissue morphology at subcellular resolution. This enables the interactive exploration of millions of transcripts and their comparison with routine histology and pathologist annotations.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/news/pathology-review-figure1.png" alt="Exploring clinical samples with molecular microscopes" width="600" height="auto" /></p>

<p>With high-resolution ST we can study tissue organization in 2D and 3D virtual tissue blocks, analyzing the organization of cells in multicellular niches and identifying which receptor–ligand interactions orchestrate their function in situ.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/news/pathology-review-figure2.png" alt="Investigating tissue organization in 2D and 3D virtual tissue blocks" width="600" height="auto" /></p>

<p>In the clinic, spatial biomarkers and patient-specific molecular mechanisms identified by ST hold great potential to inform patient care and help the discovery of novel drug targets, as showcased in early preclinical studies.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/news/pathology-review-figure3.png" alt="Clinical applications of high-resolution ST methods" width="600" height="auto" /></p>

<p>Several challenges exist to their swift clincal translation: What is the ‘best’ ST method? How do we turn complex molecular data into meaningful insights for patient care? How do we integrate in clinical routines?</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/news/pathology-review-figure4.png" alt="Current challenges in the clinical translation of high-resolution spatial transcriptomics methods" width="600" height="auto" /></p>

<p>As large-scale clinical studies are urgently needed to link spatial biomarkers with patient outcomes, we discuss key considerations for the design of clinical ST projects from sample preservation and method choice to panel design and power analysis.</p>

<p>That’s a wrap! The potential of ST to revolutionize clinical practice is huge, but we still have work to do to unlock its full impact. Stay tuned as the field evolves! 🚀</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="review article" /><category term="spatial transcriptomics" /><category term="molecular pathology" /><category term="cell–cell communication" /><category term="disease mechanism" /><category term="personalized medicine" /><category term="artificial intelligence" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Challenges &amp; Opportunities in Clinical Translation of High-Resolution Spatial Transcriptomics (ST)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our first internal Open-ST workshop!</title><link href="/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our first internal Open-ST workshop!" /><published>2024-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to organize our first internal Open-ST workshop! Colleagues from both the wet
and the dry lab came together to discuss and learn how to process Open-ST datasets.
Our aim is to teach everyone interested in learning how to analyze this kind of data,
regardless of the level of computational expertise.</p>

<p>Ultimately, we are going to offer Open-ST workshops outside of our lab. We are still
thinking about the right format for this, but if you are interested in participating
then feel free to reach out!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="openst" /><category term="workshop" /><category term="data science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to organize our first internal Open-ST workshop! Colleagues from both the wet and the dry lab came together to discuss and learn how to process Open-ST datasets. Our aim is to teach everyone interested in learning how to analyze this kind of data, regardless of the level of computational expertise.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Open-ST is published!</title><link href="/blog/openst-is-published" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open-ST is published!" /><published>2024-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/openst-is-published</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/openst-is-published"><![CDATA[<p>We developed an inexpensive, do-it-yourself, high-resolution, and open source method to quantify gene expression directly in tissues (Marie Schott, Daniel León Perinán, Elena Splendiani <i>et al</i>. <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/abstract/S0092-8674(24)00636-6">
Open-ST: High-resolution spatial transcriptomics in 3D, <i>Cell</i>, 2024</a>).
We constructed the first high-resolution molecular tumor atlas in 3D (from a single patient) and learned from these ~ 1 million sequenced cells (in tissue space) which pathways and gene programs drive phenotypes of the primary and metastatic tumor. We are currently in the lab routinely generating spatial transcriptomic data as a highly informative readout for how cells communicate within tissues/tumors and how they react to perturbations (disease mutations, perturbations from the environment (viral infection, microplastics, …).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="spatial transcriptomics" /><category term="openst" /><category term="methods development" /><category term="virtual tissue block" /><category term="lymph node" /><category term="cancer" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper on presenting a new spatial transcriptomics platform is now published!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lab webpage goes online!</title><link href="/blog/website-goes-online" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lab webpage goes online!" /><published>2024-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/website-goes-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/website-goes-online"><![CDATA[<p>The webpage of the Rajewsky Lab goes online! Feel free to explore the page and to get in touch with us.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="informative" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The webpage of the Rajewsky Lab goes online! Feel free to explore the page and to get in touch with us.]]></summary></entry></feed>