<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-05T14:44:50+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">N. Rajewsky Lab | Max Delbrück Center</title><subtitle>Systems Biology of Gene Regulatory Elements</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Our first internal Open-ST workshop!</title><link href="/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our first internal Open-ST workshop!" /><published>2024-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/first-internal-openst-workshop"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to organize our first internal Open-ST workshop! Colleagues from both the wet
and the dry lab came together to discuss and learn how to process Open-ST datasets.
Our aim is to teach everyone interested in learning how to analyze this kind of data,
regardless of the level of computational expertise.</p>

<p>Ultimately, we are going to offer Open-ST workshops outside of our lab. We are still
thinking about the right format for this, but if you are interested in participating
then feel free to reach out!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="openst" /><category term="workshop" /><category term="data science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to organize our first internal Open-ST workshop! Colleagues from both the wet and the dry lab came together to discuss and learn how to process Open-ST datasets. Our aim is to teach everyone interested in learning how to analyze this kind of data, regardless of the level of computational expertise.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Open-ST is published!</title><link href="/blog/openst-is-published" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open-ST is published!" /><published>2024-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/openst-is-published</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/openst-is-published"><![CDATA[<p>We developed an inexpensive, do-it-yourself, high-resolution, and open source method to quantify gene expression directly in tissues (Marie Schott, Daniel León Perinán, Elena Splendiani <i>et al</i>. <a href="https://www.cell.com/cell/abstract/S0092-8674(24)00636-6">
Open-ST: High-resolution spatial transcriptomics in 3D, <i>Cell</i>, 2024</a>).
We constructed the first high-resolution molecular tumor atlas in 3D (from a single patient) and learned from these ~ 1 million sequenced cells (in tissue space) which pathways and gene programs drive phenotypes of the primary and metastatic tumor. We are currently in the lab routinely generating spatial transcriptomic data as a highly informative readout for how cells communicate within tissues/tumors and how they react to perturbations (disease mutations, perturbations from the environment (viral infection, microplastics, …).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="spatial transcriptomics" /><category term="openst" /><category term="methods development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper on presenting a new spatial transcriptomics platform is now published!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lab webpage goes online!</title><link href="/blog/website-goes-online" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lab webpage goes online!" /><published>2024-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/website-goes-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/website-goes-online"><![CDATA[<p>The webpage of the Rajewsky Lab goes online! Feel free to explore the page and to get in touch with us.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="informative" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The webpage of the Rajewsky Lab goes online! Feel free to explore the page and to get in touch with us.]]></summary></entry></feed>